<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Express | Ringo Cheung]]></title>
  <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/blog/categories/express/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-30T13:21:57-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ringfather.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ringo Cheung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bookshelf]]></title>
    <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/bookshelf/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T22:11:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ringfather.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/bookshelf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Worked through the yeoman tutorial. In my opinion not useful until understanding of the mean stack is already mastered &ndash; took about 1.5 hours. Worked through two tutorials on scotch.io, starting to get how the parts of the application are put together &ndash; the node API queries the MongoDB database and provides CRUD operations for the Angular part to use.</p>

<p>Will need to figure out a way to query an open database for books when users type in book title, author, etc. will need functionality in the get function so users can get by title, author and others. First, work through the API creation tutorials and user auth as these are critical parts of any application.</p>

<p>Idea is to work through enough tutorials to understand how to create a basic CRUD app, and then start to focus specifically on bookshelf. Goal for tomorrow (Saturday, August 23rd) is to finish the back end tutorials, including user auth, set up the Schemas for bookshelf and then start working through the Angular tutorial. Ideal case is to actually finish the Angular tutorial.</p>

<p>Finished the Node API tutorial. I get how to create an api now that can CRUD. For bookshelf, each new user will have to have a json object containing an array of book objects which point to a book. Need to figure out how to create this complex structure.
Not sure how to actually use the api in the front-end of the application yet.</p>

<p>It is 08-26, 4 days since I started this project and the API is nearly complete. It currently supports requesting and adding friends, adding (and automatically creating if DNE) books to lists, deleting books from lists and creating, reading and deleting user information. Final components of API are to allow users to delete friends and to update their email. Current user model identifies users based on username which is convenient since they must be unique. Going to start version controlling this app now that I&rsquo;ve grasped the basics of the back end.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
