<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: YNCN | Ringo Cheung]]></title>
  <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/blog/categories/yncn/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-23T15:38:48-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ringfather.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ringo Cheung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[YNCN Interviews - Freddy Chen]]></title>
    <link href="http://ringfather.github.io/blog/2015/01/23/yncn-interviews-freddy-chen/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-23T14:53:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ringfather.github.io/blog/2015/01/23/yncn-interviews-freddy-chen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ringo: This is the first post in what I hope to be a series of interviews with successful alumni from UofT Engineering. The idea of these posts is to give students an idea of the different paths these alumni have taken to get to where they are in their career now. Hopefully, the ideas and techniques in these posts will help you in your own job search! Please feel free to send any feedback to <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x72;&#x69;&#x6e;&#x67;&#111;&#x2e;&#99;&#x68;&#x65;&#117;&#110;&#x67;&#64;&#x79;&#x6f;&#117;&#114;&#x65;&#110;&#x65;&#x78;&#x74;&#46;&#x63;&#97;">&#114;&#x69;&#110;&#x67;&#111;&#46;&#99;&#x68;&#x65;&#x75;&#110;&#103;&#64;&#121;&#111;&#117;&#x72;&#101;&#110;&#101;&#120;&#x74;&#46;&#99;&#97;</a></p>

<h6>Introduction</h6>

<br>


<p>Hi everyone! My name is Freddy. I’m an ECE1T3T1. I didn’t do PEY, but I still took a year off. We’ll get to that later. I’m currently a Software Engineer at Airbnb. I interned at Facebook, Fixmo, and Altera. I also spent a summer working on my own startup with The Next 36.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I remember when I first got to the University of Toronto&hellip; I had no idea what I wanted to do. There were a lot of things that I learned along the way, so I will try my best to pass on some knowledge and advice. I’ll start with some standard You’re Next questions, then answer some questions I’ve gotten from a lot of younger students over the years.</p>

<p>Oh, and before we begin, just know that there are many ways to succeed. You can choose to ignore everything that I say and still be fine. These are some things that I did to get me started in the software industry.</p>

<h6>Q: What was on your resume?</h6>

<br>


<p>You can check out my LinkedIn account <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/freddychen">here</a>.I honestly don’t know why these haven’t replaced resumes yet&hellip; they’re so much better in every way!</p>

<p>For paper resumes, I tried to keep my stuff to one page. Your most relevant and impressive experiences can most likely be summed up in one page. There are plenty of resources online about what you should have in your resume. Go look them up!</p>

<p>Oh, the most common question that I get is probably “Does my GPA matter?”. The answer is a resounding YES… of course it matters. Everything on your resume is a signal for whether or not you should be hired (otherwise it’s probably a waste of space…). Don’t be discouraged if you have a low GPA though. Highlight your other strengths and experiences and let those shine through!</p>

<h6>Q: How did you apply for your jobs?</h6>

<br>


<p>My friend hates getting this question because his answer is “I applied online”. And guess what? My answer is actually the same! But okay, there are some tricks (obviously very specific to the software industry).</p>

<p>If you’re looking at big companies in Canada, chances are the PEY office has partnerships already (IBM, AMD, etc.). If you’re looking for big companies in the US (Google, Apple, Microsoft, Amazon, etc.), usually applying online will get you an interview if your resume looks good. Having friends who’ve interned at those companies help as well. They can refer you to their recruiter.</p>

<p>If you’re looking to get into the cool and hip startups in Silicon Valley, you can try looking at the portfolios of Venture Capital companies and applying online. Again, referrals help here.</p>

<p>The best way of applying for jobs I think is through networking. I had friends who worked in Silicon Valley that connected me with a recruiter for a Venture Capital firm. That’s how I got considered for Facebook and Airbnb.</p>

<h6>Q: How did you prepare for interviews?</h6>

<br>


<p>I practiced a lot of coding on paper and on the computer. I reviewed computer science concepts and practiced explaining them. I bought <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Programming-Questions/dp/098478280X">Cracking the Coding Interview</a> and practiced from that. I didn’t read the whole book, but I understood a lot of the basics. I went on glassdoor.com and careercup.com to look up interview questions. I never did any practice on topcoder. I did mock interviews with my friends (as the interviewer and interviewee).</p>

<p>You should do whatever you need to do to feel prepared though. Everyone learns differently.</p>

<h6>Q: What would you do differently if you could go back in time?</h6>

<br>


<p>I wish I prepared harder in first year and second year to try to get a job. Don’t believe it when people tell you that companies don’t hire first or second years. Companies look for specific skills and experiences, not what year of university you’re in. However, if you don’t have any significant skills or experiences, the year of university that you’re in is used as a proxy. If you are able to prove that you qualify for the job and that you’re one of their best candidates, you will get the job.</p>

<p>The first coding interview I walked into was with Microsoft. I totally bombed it because I had no idea what to expect. Always go prepared!</p>

<h6>Q: Should I do PEY?</h6>

<br>


<p>If you’re interested in being in the software industry, probably not. A lot of software engineering intern projects are well scoped out and only last a couple of months. You don’t need 12 to 16 months to learn the ropes and ship something meaningful.</p>

<p>Ever wonder why there are so many more Waterloo software engineers down in Silicon Valley? Their co-op program is designed to maximize the amount of work experience you have before you graduate by alternating between work and school every 4 months. By the time a Waterloo software engineer graduates, they have probably already worked for around 4-6 different companies. Waterloo has built up such a good reputation that a lot of first years there with little to no experience are able to get jobs as QA engineers at the very least.</p>

<p>So what can aspiring software engineers from U of T do to catch up? And yes, I’m using the term “catch up” because let’s face it, the software engineers from Waterloo are killing it. What we can do is to take a year off instead of doing PEY, and try filling that time with internships with different companies. If you’re really good you can probably work at 3-4 differen companies. Some companies aren’t very open to this (Microsoft wouldn’t hire me outside of the summer… they would only do it for Waterloo engineers), but you should try anyway. Worst case scenario, you should at least try for a 12 month work term plus a summer internship.</p>

<h6>Q: I want to just chill for a summer. Can I do that?</h6>

<br>


<p>You can do anything you want, but there’s a big chance you’re going to fall behind some of your peers in terms of work or research experience. Whether you like it or not, you’re at a pretty critical time in your life, and if you don’t want to fall behind, you should try your best to maximize your chance for success.</p>

<p>I’m going to do my own startup because I have this amazing idea and I want to change the world.</p>

<p>Awesome. Canada needs more entrepreneurs like you. I would advise you to really put everything you got into it though. If you’re going to do a startup for 4 or 12 or 16 months, make sure you put your all into it. Be prepared to postpone school if things go well. I strongly believe you won’t make it big if you’re half-assing it, doing it on the side, doing it temporarily, doing it cause everyone else is doing it, or anything like that. Choose something that you strongly believe in, do the research, make sure your idea makes sense, and then put your all into it.</p>

<h6>Q: I have no work experience, my resume is meh, and I don’t know anyone that can refer me to any awesome companies. What do I do?</h6>

<br>


<p>Network. Go out there and meet people. Maybe you don’t think you have enough talent or experience to offer, maybe you’re too shy, maybe your parents are telling you to study, maybe your friends are having an awesome party that you have to go to, but think about it: this is your career and your future. If you’re serious about getting a great job out of school, then I would say that the upside to putting yourself out there is much greater than being embarrassed by your peers, falling a little behind in class, or missing out on an awesome party. Remember: you miss 100% of the shots that you don’t take.</p>

<p>Oh, and for the record, if networking opportunities present themselves at parties, definitely go to those instead of studying an extra 3-4 hours for something you’ve already studied a lot for. Meeting people and nurturing relationships in university is critical for success after university.</p>

<p>Once you meet some people you can look up to, ask them for help. Ask them how they got there, and ask them to mentor you. Take their advice and go spend the time to improve your skills. Nobody starts out at a superstar. Set consistent goals for yourself and go achieve them! You can do it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
